<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Intrigues of love: or, The amours and gallantries of the French court, during the reign of that amorous and warlike prince Henry IV. (Surnamed the Great.) Being a true and pleasant history. Newly made English from the French, By Sir Edwine Sadleyr Baronet</title>
            <title>Histoire des amours du grand Alcandre. English</title>
            <author>Conti, Louise-Marguerite de Lorraine, princesse de, 1574-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80380</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5955C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226033</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897222</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170822</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80380)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170822)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2477:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Intrigues of love: or, The amours and gallantries of the French court, during the reign of that amorous and warlike prince Henry IV. (Surnamed the Great.) Being a true and pleasant history. Newly made English from the French, By Sir Edwine Sadleyr Baronet</title>
                  <title>Histoire des amours du grand Alcandre. English</title>
                  <author>Conti, Louise-Marguerite de Lorraine, princesse de, 1574-1631.</author>
                  <author>Sadleir, Edwin, Sir, d. 1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R.G. and sold by Benj. Crayle at the Peacock and Bible, at the West end of St. Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Possibly a translation of Histoire des amours du grand Alcandre, by Louise-Marguerite de Lorraine, princesse de Conti. (Cf. B.N. Cat.)</note>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Louise-Marguerite de Lorraine, princesse de Conti.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi1 A⁴ B-I⁶ K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Court and courtiers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170822:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> INTRIGUES OF LOVE: OR, THE AMOURS AND GALLANTRIES OF THE FRENCH Court, During the Reign of that Amorous and Warlike Prince HENRY IV. (Surnamed the Great.) Being a true and pleaſant Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Newly made</hi> Engliſh <hi>from the</hi> French, <hi>By Sir</hi> Edwine Sadleyr <hi>Baronet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. G.</hi> and ſold by <hi>Benj. Crayle</hi> at the Peacock and Bible, at the Weſt end of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170822:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170822:2"/>
            <head>To his Belov'd Conſort THE LADY, <hi>S—</hi>In return for the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal from Her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd.</head>
            <p>THE firſt Fruits of my Pen (My Dear) are at thy Feet, <hi>The Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Amours of King</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170822:3"/> HENRY <hi>the Fourth,</hi> (Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam'd <hi>the Great)</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> as in an <hi>Engliſh dreſs,</hi> (ſo far they being properly and genuinely my own) and I hope not unfaithfully render'd from their native French, wherein it is pitty (tho ſo Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant a Language) that the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties they contain ſhould have ſo long lain hid; (from ſuch at leaſt who are unſeen in that Tongue.) Whether now I have perform'd with an equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent ſucceſs, and made my Author ſpeak <hi>Engliſh</hi> with the ſame advantage as he doth his <hi>French,</hi> I muſt leave Thee and
<pb facs="tcp:170822:3"/> my Readers to judge. I know, I have endeavour'd to do him Juſtice, and ſo to Copy from the fair Original, as not to leave ſo much as one good Lineament behind; and if I have fail'd in this Attempt, I ſhall yet have this honour, to fall a Sacrifice to Thy Self, and the better Sex, (for whom the following Leaves are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally intended) and it ſhall be my Boaſt that I am ſuch a Sacrifice. But may Thy Self and thoſe Created Dèities, but ſmile upon this firſt Eſſay, and the Encouragement may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb facs="tcp:170822:4"/> ſome better Services from Thine and Theirs eternally obſequious.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170822:4"/>
            <head>The Author's Addreſs to the Reader.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REader, 'tis not the Epidemick itch,</l>
               <l>That oft ſo many does bewitch,</l>
               <l>That odd fantaſtick ſtrange Diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>That makes men luſt ſo much for Praiſe;</l>
               <l>No ſuch Capricio prompt me on</l>
               <l>To undertake what here is done.</l>
               <l>Let then the Learn'd conteſt the Bays,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Although the free commodity of Wit,</l>
               <l>Was ne're Monopolized yet,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvail'd th'enſuing Hiſt'ry lies,</l>
               <l>Seeking alone the ambition'd Prize,</l>
               <l>The bleſſing of the Ladies Eyes;</l>
               <l>Before whoſe Altars 'tis a Sacrifice.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:170822:5"/>
            <head>A l'Autheur ſur ſon Ingeniuſe Traducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Epigramme.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AUtantque dureront les Intrigues d'Amour,</l>
               <l>Tandiſque ſur des Coeurs Cupid aura l'Empire,</l>
               <l>Les Hommes ſi long temps, &amp; les Dames de Cour,</l>
               <l>Cette Traduction prendront plaiſir à lire.</l>
               <l>Elle eſt douce, elle eſt mâle, elle eſt pleine d'attrais,</l>
               <l>certainement elle eſt fidelle;</l>
               <l>Si le Francois eſt bon, meilleur en eſt l'Anglois,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Si l'Autheur ne paroiſt, c eſt, qu il vole fort haut</l>
               <l>Parmy les Traducteurs il vole, comme l'Aigle</l>
               <l>Au deſſus des autres cyſeaux</l>
               <l>Lors qu'elle prend l'Eſſort, &amp; vole à tire d'ailes</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>P. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:170822:5"/>
            <head>To the Author on his Ingenious Tranſlation.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS the skill'd <hi>Gard'ner</hi> doth, by kind remove</l>
               <l>The growth and beauty of rich Plants im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</l>
               <l>With no leſs my ſtick skill, kind Sir, you here</l>
               <l>Tranſplant, and better from the <hi>Gallick</hi> Air;</l>
               <l>Lo here an instance, of its choicest Fruit,</l>
               <l>Whilſt richer Juices feed th'impov'riſh'd Root.</l>
               <l>'Twould pleaſe (methinks) Great <hi>HENRY's</hi> Shade to ſee</l>
               <l>This noble Task ſo well perform'd by thee.</l>
               <l>Smiling, the Story of his <hi>Loves</hi> he'd read,</l>
               <l>And bleſs the Hand that rais'd him from the Dead;</l>
               <l>That Hand that gives him hopes to live as long</l>
               <l>And great in'th'<hi>Engliſh</hi> as the <hi>Gallick</hi> Tongue.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>France</hi> then no more thy nobler Climate boaſt,</l>
               <l>Since we perform as well, and with leſs coſt:</l>
               <l>The naked Matter, true, we do receive,</l>
               <l>Yet Life and Spirit to that Matter give,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:170822:6"/>
               <l> Th'unpolliſh'd Lump inveſts it ſelf anew,</l>
               <l>Casts off its old, and takes a nobler Hue.</l>
               <l>Ev'n as the <hi>Snake</hi> its tatter'd skin lays by,</l>
               <l>And through that means grows fairer to the eye.</l>
               <l>Since then, Dear Sir, here in few vacant hours,</l>
               <l>With ſuch ſucceſs you can Tranſplant theſe Flowers,</l>
               <l>Let ſome freſh Subject flow from your ſoft Pen.</l>
               <l>Charm the fair Sex, and gain the praiſe of Men.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>B. C.</signed>
               </closer>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170822:6"/>
            <head>THE AMOURS OF King <hi>HENRY</hi> the Fourth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>KIng <hi>Henry</hi> the Great arriving in histurn to his Succeſſion, in the Kingdom of his Anceſtors; found no little difficulty in putting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into Poſſeſſion, for as much as he was of the new Religion, and for the Rancounters which he upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count met with from many of the Greateſt of his Subjects, that would not acknowledge him, (the moſt part alſo of the principal Cities and wall'd Towns holding of their Party) it behoved him in good earneſt to labour for ſo brave, and honourable an intereſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt Arms that he took up was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170822:7"/> 
               <hi>Normandy:</hi> But that which there paſs' (both at <hi>Arques</hi> and at <hi>Diepe)</hi> being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by moſt Hiſtorians of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Times, I ſhall here praetermit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf with the Relation only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what I have both learnt and ſeen in his Court.</p>
            <p>In the time of the Royal <hi>Henry</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Third, there was a counteſs i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Guienne</hi> of whom he was very much enamour'd the Counteſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who appear'd to be the ſole and unrival'd Monarch of his Will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe being the only Favorites whom ſhe recommended, and amongſt the reſt the Marqueſs of <hi>Parabere,</hi> whoſe Siſter was at that time with this Lady. But he meets another Lady in his paſſage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Frontiers of <hi>Normandy</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to whoſe new Conqueſt the firſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt reſign. <note n="*" place="bottom">Widow of <hi>Philibert</hi> Earl of <hi>Gramont,</hi> who dy'd at the Siege of <hi>La Fere,</hi> in the Year, 1580.</note> A Widow young and of ſo amiable an appearance in the Eyes of this Great Prince, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170822:7"/> with eaſe he forgot her to whom he had made ſo many contrary Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And in truth, ſhe had thoſe Charms that were not to be found in the firſt. Both being of equal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the <note n="*" place="bottom">The Marchioneſs of <hi>Guercheville</hi> was Anthoinette of <hi>Pons,</hi> firſt Wife to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Sylly</hi> Earl of <hi>Roche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guion;</hi> and ſecond to <hi>Charles du Pleſſis,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancourt,</hi> firſt Eſquire of <hi>France,</hi> and Governour of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note> Marchioneſs of <hi>Guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheville</hi> (ſuch was the Name of the latter) being Educated in the faireſt and beſt govern'd Court of thoſe times, that I mean of the deceaſed King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, a Prince, than whom none knew better to play the King and rule his Honours, and all things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to Majeſty.</p>
            <p>To her therefore this new Captive Prince gave himſelf wholly up; and In ſuch ſort forgot the Counteſs of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> as that nothing remain'd of her in his memory but her very Name. And the Marqueſs of <hi>Parabere,</hi> who had been the Confident of that Amour, could do no leſs than tell him, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170822:8"/> he ought at leaſt to conſerve a Friendſhip that he had all his Life-time profeſs'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tho tranſported by his new Amour no other thoughts could poſſeſs him, but thoſe of motioning a Marriage to the Marchioneſs of <hi>Guercheville,</hi> whom he knew would not harken to him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other terms.</p>
            <p>His Love-affair being in this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, he advances towards his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, whom the main concern, the proſecution of his Imperial Right, which ſo unjuſtly they would extort from him, doth neceſſitate him to attend; and is by ſo many good Succeſſes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd, that he undertakes the Siege of <hi>Paris. Sed cedant iterum arma Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidini,</hi> But Love, an unſeaſonable God, muſt revel again, though in the midſt of Arms; A young and Beautiful
<note n="*" place="bottom">The Abeſs of <hi>Montmartre</hi> was called, <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Beauvilliers,</hi> Daughter to the Earl of St. <hi>Aignan.</hi>
               </note> Abeſs of <hi>Montmartre</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Clairemont,</hi> ſtrikes him at this ſiege, and ſo infatuates the Royal Lover, that the Siege being yet dubious, he takes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170822:8"/> her away from <hi>Montmartre,</hi> and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her to be conducted to <hi>Senlis</hi> (a Town under his Obedience,) ſhe reigns the Miſtreſs of his heart for ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Marchioneſs of <hi>Guercheville,</hi> that his Honour may not be too much blotted by her deſertion) is to be ſome Eminent <note n="*" place="bottom">The Lords of his Court is Monſieur de <hi>Lyancourt</hi> before mentioned.</note> Lord of his Court, and the King Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diates the Match, ſoliciting her as much now, in favour of her new Lover, as before he had done of himſelf. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto therefore yielding a modeſt Ear to the King, ſhe is periwaded to the Match; receiving the Royal Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (as ſhall afterwards be related) that ſhe continued ſtill in his Favour. After the accompliſhment of this deſign, the King taking his rounds to confirm and eſtabliſh his Authority, comes in the end to <hi>Mantes,</hi> whither the Ladies having reſorted, had made ſome figure of a Court, ſo fair a concourſe of Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170822:9"/> and particularly thoſe of Quality, whoſe Brothers and Husbands heknew, and who had been ſo much at his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, gave no ſmall pleaſure to the King. The reſt, who in his younger age he had known in the Courts of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, he treated likewiſe with all Civility, and receiv'd from them no leſs than an anſwerable reſpect.</p>
            <p>Some time before his arrival to this place, the Duke of <hi>Bellgard</hi> (an old Favourite of the deceaſed King <hi>Henry</hi>'s) had Characteris'd to him the Beauty of a young Lady (a proper Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſo amorous a Prince) with whom he was very much inamour'd, and as ſhe was to admiration Fair, ſo he could not forbear to Commend her; She was not at that time at <hi>Mantes,</hi> and the Relation of the Duke of <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> had excited in the King a Curioſity to ſee her; but his affairs would not ſuffer him for this time, though ſoon after when he departed thence for <hi>Senlis,</hi> he obtain'd the deſire he had of ſeeing Madam <hi>D'Eſtree</hi> (ſuch was the Name
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170822:9"/> of <hi>Bellgard</hi>'s Miſtreſs) and at <hi>Senlis</hi> entertains her with all the poſſible Gallantries, that his time would give him leave to perform; which done, and departing from thence, after the ſeeing of many other places, he returns to <hi>Mantes,</hi> where the unfortunate <hi>Bellgard</hi> asking his leave to go ſee his Miſtreſs, too late diſcovers that his own Tongue had betray'd him to the loſs of her, and that the King had been too much taken with the ſight of her at <hi>Senlis;</hi> thus prov'd the poor lover the Author of his own misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; and indeed we are all too often more obnoxious to hurt from our ſelves than others. By this view doth he looſe not only the permiſſion of ſeeing of his Miſtreſs, but hazard the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his Maſter and the good hour of his Fortune.</p>
            <p>Some time before, he had ſtay'd long at <hi>Mantes,</hi> and had been extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ill; the Ladies that was there, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Him all the conrteſie and aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that they could, and amongſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170822:10"/> the reſt the young and beautious Madam <hi>de Humieres,</hi> who was reſolv'd to approve herſelf to him by her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, not only for the reputation that he had of being one of the greateſt Gallants of the Age, but alſo for that particular eſteem ſhe had for his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. This accident gave a fair opper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to expreſs her reſpects to the fair Madam <hi>d'Humieres,</hi> and to the afflicted Duke to receive them, who was ſo happy as by this to find an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, which he might otherways have long ſought for and in vain. But not ſo great are the Lover's long, for <hi>Bellgard</hi> upon a viſit to the <note n="*" place="bottom">The Lord of <hi>Eſtree</hi> was <hi>John Antonie</hi> of <hi>Eſtree,</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Caeuvers</hi> who had married <hi>Franceſs Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou,</hi> of <hi>du Bourdaiſſere,</hi>
               </note> Lord of <hi>Eſtree,</hi> falls paſſionately in Love with his fair Daughter the aforeſaid Madam <hi>d'Eſtree;</hi> Who tho at firſt ſhe with ſome reluctancy received, (Loving and being belov'd of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>d'Villars,</hi> a perſon, moſt amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and deſerving,) yet was ſhe not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170822:10"/> long cruel; being alſo paſſionately in Love with her new Lover, to whom the Admiral (ſeeing clearly what was moſt for her intereſt) offers a thouſand reproaches, which ſerv'd only to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Rival in his Affairs, and ſo began to neglect her, that inſtead of reclaiming her from her other Lover, he threw her into an utter deſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his Affection.</p>
            <p>It was now that the King became inamour'd of Madam <hi>d'Eſtree</hi> the Miſtreſs of <hi>Bell'gard,</hi> tho through the importancy of his Affairs inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly diverting him another way, he could ſee her but once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Voiage; however in his Heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the kindled Fires, and is of nothing more thoughtful during the Voiage than of her, which is long enough.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <note n="*" place="bottom">The Duke of <hi>Languille</hi> was <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Orleans,</hi> who afterwards Married <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Gonzakes,</hi> Daughter of the Duke of <hi>Nevers,</hi>
               </note> Duke of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueville</hi> (no more proof againſt the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170822:11"/> of the blind God than her other Lovers,) at <hi>Mantes</hi> commenceth Captive to the All-conqu'ring Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> a Lady ſo univerſally effectual by her Charms upon all that beheld her, that to love and look upon her, was only Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonimous Terms, or terms expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the ſelf ſame thing.</p>
            <p>This Prince had before lov'd Madam <hi>d'Humieres,</hi> the late beautious Subject of our Pen, who having loſt her firſt Lover, had now imbarq'd herſelf a freſh. And indeed ſo little conſtant was he always to his choice, that he lov'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſent beſt, whilſt Madam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> on the other ſide, who thought to too inſufferable a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction from her Excellences to be without an admirer, had likewiſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd herſelf afreſh.</p>
            <p>This intreague continu'd during the Voiage of the King; but he reſents it ſo ſtrongly at his return, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes moſt furiouſly jealous, inſomuch that he began to remit of his favour
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170822:11"/> to <hi>Bellgard,</hi> giving him to underſtand that he would no more of a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in his Amours, than in that of his Kingdome, and that his paſſion was dearer to him than any thing elſe. <hi>Bellgard</hi> was troubled at this Language and more eſpecially at the tone and action with which it was delivered, and promiſed the King all he deſired; whilſt Madamoiſell <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> who lov'd not the King, and had beſtow'd all her Affections upon another, was ſo inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terately inrag'd, that ſhe proteſted ſhe could not love him, and ceaſt not to reproach him with the hindrance of her Marriage to the Duke of <hi>Bellgar'd</hi> that made his Court to that end, and immediatly departed <hi>Mantes,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd herſelf to her Fathers Houſe.</p>
            <p>The King, to whom his Enemies never gave any aſtoniſhment, conceiv'd ſo great an impreſſion from this Action of his Miſtreſs, that he knew not what to reſolve upon. Sometimes he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy's with himſelf that ſeeing her the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170822:12"/> next day might reduce her to her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer clemency. But this pleas'd him not in Company, and to go alone was matter of the extreamiſt hazard, War being of all ſides of him, and two Garriſons of his Enemies in his way which muſt lie through the great and waſt Forreſt; ſo that he could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with himſelf what Counſel to take but his paſſion ſurmounting all, cauſeth him not withſtanding, to undertake the Journey; four Leagues of which he rides on Horſeback, accompany'd by five of the moſt Truſty of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; And being come within three leagues of the Ladies Houſe, he Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes the habit of a Peaſant, puts a ſack of Chaff upon his Back, and goes thither on foot, (having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence it ſeems the day before where he ſhould ſee her) and find her in a Gallery, with only her Siſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with her, who was eſpous'd to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Marqueſs of <hi>Villar</hi>'s</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170822:12"/>
            <p> She was ſo ſurpriz'd to find the King <note n="*" place="bottom">Madam of <hi>Eſtreé,</hi> the Perſon meant by She, was ſo ſurpris'd, &amp;c. was Siſter to <hi>Hippolite Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liette</hi> of <hi>Eſtreé</hi> Daughter to the Lord of <hi>Eſtreé,</hi> and Wife he ſays to the Marqueſs of <hi>Villars</hi> or <hi>Ceriſay</hi> being ſtyled as well one as the other, and afterwards one of the King's Miſtreſſes upon the deceaſe of her Siſter.</note> in ſuch an Equipage, and ſo ill ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with a Change that appear'd ſo ridiculous in him, that ſhe gave him but an ill Reception, yet this rather for the Cloaths that he had on than for himſelf, and ſtaid but juſt long enough with him to let him know that they misbecom'd him ſo much ſhe could not look upon him, and ſo left him.</p>
            <p>Her Siſter more civil, excuſeth her coldneſs, and perſwaded him that it was the fear only of her Father that caus'd her to retire, and did all that ſhe could to qualifie ſuch a diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which indeed was a thing not difficult for her to do, he being a Prince ſo effectually captivated that nothing could looſe him from his chains. Now
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170822:13"/> as this Voiage was not only perilous, but to very little purpoſe, ſo it put the people into an equal aſtoniſhment to think what ſhould become of the King.</p>
            <p>He reduceth them to their former Temper at his return, and to the end, that he might no more be rack'd by ſo ungrateful a thing as a diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this caſe, he invents this ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem to remove the cauſe; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this Lady to whom the hinted abſence was imputed under colour therefore of his ſervice, (the old Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman being under ſome Provincial Truſt,) he cauſeth him to come and live at <hi>Mantes,</hi> (not a little pleas'd with the happy acqueſt of his deſire,) the means of ſeeing his Miſtreſs as often as he ſhould have thought fit, if the neceſſity of his occaſions had not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd him another way.</p>
            <p>In the interim, we muſt not paſs ver the adventure of the <note n="*" place="bottom">The Marqueſs of <hi>Humieres</hi> was <hi>Giles</hi> of <hi>Conflans Armantiere</hi> Son to the Earl of <hi>Auchy.</hi>
               </note> Marqueſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170822:13"/> 
               <hi>d'Humieres,</hi> who at the Age of two and twenty years defended the Town of <hi>Senlis,</hi> during the rigour of a great Siege, running the very utmoſt hazard of his life, and ſuſteining two ſuch great Aſſaults, that it was contrary to the opinion of all thoſe that was with him in the Garriſon and even of the Governour himſelf; not yeilding the leaſt to Capitulate, but bravely and ſtoutly maintaining it, till ſuch time as he gave oppertunity to the King's Servants to relieve the place, who haſten'd in their relief as ſoon as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the chiefeſt being related to the Marqueſs, not inſenſible of his dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and unwilling he ſhould be loſt where he alſo gain'd a <note n="*" place="bottom">The Battle fought at <hi>Senlis,</hi> in the month of <hi>May,</hi> 1589.</note> moſt memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Battle, and much advanced the affairs of the King on that ſide the River <hi>Loire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This young Warrier in ſo green an Age, had rendred a thouſand Proofs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170822:14"/> of his Vallour, and had thought of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hitherto but his Honour. But after this ſo brave and Maſculine an Action, having not only rais'd the Siege and diſcomfited the Enemy, but alſo trayl'd in the greateſt part of their Cannon into the Town, and nail'd down the reſt, he begins to bethink himſelf of ſome diverſion. And at <hi>Mantes,</hi> whether he went for that purpoſe, the Hero that before had ſmil'd at the reports of Cannon, and fruſtrated the improſperous aims of his adverſaries at <hi>Senlis</hi> Siege, is by the reſiſtleſs powers of Love and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wounded and incaptiv'd; the fair Object was Madam <hi>d'Simie,</hi> whom ſeeing there he fell moſt paſſionately in Love with. This Lady beſides her beauty, was ſo agreeable, and had ſo many Charms, that ſhe put him into ſuch a condition that he had neither Eyes nor Thoughts but what was hers; this continued wholly unperceiv'd for ſome time, and the Husband of this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170822:14"/> Lady was the laſt of thoſe that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd it, the Husband I mean of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>d'Simie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But no ſooner came it to his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, but all over enrag'd, and in a jealous and brutiſh fury he conveys her away to a Caſtle more fit for Lions than for her, yet notwithſtanding is careful neither to ſay nor do any thing that might enrage the Marqueſs <hi>d'Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mieres,</hi> having no deſire to grapple with ſo rude and potent an Enimy; but during this Treatment of the Lady, the Marqueſs however contrives with himſelf to releive her, and to apply a remedy, with which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of Affairs doth furniſh him; indeed he did not eſteem it the beſt, yet it was ſuch as ſerv'd at the leaſt to the main purpoſe, to redeem his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs from her Priſon.</p>
            <p>Now the King being return'd back from his Voiage to <hi>Mantes,</hi> Beſieges and takes the Town of <hi>Diepe,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Government of it to <hi>Simie</hi> who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170822:15"/> retir'd thither with his Wife. This fair and commodious place miniſters an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunity to the Marqueſs <hi>d'Humieres,</hi> of having ſome intelligence of his Miſtreſs, who us'd all imaginable means to continue his amour. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe therefore ho cauſeth a Chriſtning to be made, to which Madam <hi>d'Simie</hi> and her Husband are invited; who could not fail to come ſince they were perſons of ſuch Quality that invited them, and their Company likewiſe ſo much ſolicited by their own Relations, but the Marqueſs <hi>d'Humiere</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>d'Simie</hi> could not here be diſcreet enough, perhaps through a little too much rapture with the interview, to prevent the Jealouſie of her Husband from breaking out, and almoſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it ſelf in the horrid Murther of his own Wife, whom he brings back to his own Habitation, takes away all her Servants and claps her up cloſe in a Chamber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D'Humieres,</hi> inform'd of this ill
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170822:15"/> uſage, ſought all poſſible means to redreſs it, but could not openly attempt it, leaſt it might juſtifie the conceived <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ealouſies of <hi>Simie,</hi> who would certainly upon this have kill'd his Wife. The next recourſe therefore that he made, was the ſeeking ſome occaſion to die, to which end he thoughtfully retires himſelf to one of his
<note n="*" place="bottom">The Caſtle of <hi>Ham</hi> in <hi>Piccardy.</hi>
               </note> Caſtles, where all the Nobility and Gentry coming to viſit him, and obſerving ſo many of them together, he propoſeth an Adventure of Storming an adjacent Caſtle of the Enemies in open day; which Motion, though all at the firſt reſiſted, (ſuch an-Enterprize appearing to be too hazardous in the day-time,) yet in fine, overcome by his perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they unanimouſly conſent, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therefore along with him ſome of his Infantry, he comes at ſo lucky an hour to the Caſtle, that applying his Petards he blew open one of the Gates,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170822:16"/> the Guards of the Caſtle being then gone off; but the Inhabitants reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, let fly a Volley of Muſquets, and ſo ruffly ſaluted the head of this young Generous Warrier, that at once it put an end to his growing Lawrels and his Love; having ſcarce yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the Age of 22 Years. When the King heard this, he infinitely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it, not only for thoſe Services which he had already receiv'd from him, but alſo for thoſe which he might very probably have expected from ſo much Vertue if he had liv'd. And I think I am oblig'd to give him the Character, of being one of the generouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Men, and one of the Valianteſt perhaps of the Age.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>d'Simie,</hi> bore this Death very impatiently for a little while, but no ſooner did ſhe ſomething re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her ſelf, but ſhe ſolaceth with the thoughts of a new Amour. Thus far Madam <hi>d'Humieres</hi> and her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170822:16"/>
            <p> During all this interval, Madam <hi>d'Eſtree</hi> continues her Affection to the Duke of <hi>Bellgard,</hi> notwithſtanding her Amour with the King. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise gives incouragement to the Duke of <hi>Longueville,</hi> both writing to him and receiving Letters from him; But <hi>Bellgard</hi> reſolves to deſiſt, and not hazard his Good grace with the King, for the loſs of a Miſtreſs which he might ſo eaſily regain. And <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueville</hi> too, ſeeing his Prince return, Entreats back the Letters ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from him, promiſing to do her the ſame Juſtice without diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Affection to her. In brief, he manag'd the buſineſs ſo well, that the time and place are appointed this action, but in Contradiction to to his Promiſe, deceives her of the moſt Important part of what he had receiv'd from her, thinking to Influence her by this politick Reſerve, and to aw and oblige her to his Will. But ſo mortally provoked is Madam
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170822:17"/> 
               <hi>d'Eſtree</hi> with this Gullery, that in the end it coſt no leſs than the Life of this Prince.</p>
            <p>For ceaſing not from this time to render him all the ill offices to the King; and the Duke not induring the Diſpleaſure which he receiv'd from the King upon it, becomes a Party againſt him, and at his entrance into the Town of <hi>Daurlens,</hi> finiſhed his Life by the receit of a Muſquet ſhot upon his Head. People generally believing that Madam <hi>d'Eſtree</hi> had now obtain'd her deſire in his diſpatch. Thus end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> for having been too politick.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Lord of <hi>Eſtree</hi> the Father of this Lady, much troubled to ſee the Royal Amour each minute ſo much advancing, was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to rid himſelf of this Tyranny. The moſt probable and equitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for which, ſeem'd to be to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170822:17"/> Marry her; And a <note n="*" place="bottom">Nicholas Damerval, <hi>Lord of</hi> Lyancourt, <hi>which near to</hi> Neſteen <hi>in</hi> Piccardy.</note> Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity in the Country offering himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o this end, of an Eſtate not incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etent for the allyance, (though of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Body as much deform'd as his Mind) Madam <hi>d'Eſtree</hi> conſents, yet Swares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he King not only to be preſent at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay of her Nuptials, but that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould ſo emphatically conveigh her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>way thence from the ſight of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Husband, that ſhe ſhould never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee him again, or at leaſt, not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe than by the King's permiſſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſwading him that ſhe could never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſent to any that ſhould make her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfaithful to him.</p>
            <p>But the Day paſſing, and the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot being there, (who was now ingag'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an enterpriſe of importance,) ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wears a hundred Oaths to be reveng'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the King, and yet that ſhe would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot lye with her Husband who think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170822:18"/> his Authority over her, would be greater in his own Houſe than in the Town he Married her in, over which the Lord of <hi>Eſtree</hi> was Governour, carries her away thither, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding cauſed herſelf to be ſo well accompany'd by the Ladies her Kinſwomen that were at the Wedding, that he durſt not attempt any thing upon her, but what was pleaſing; and the King arriving in the interim at the next Town, commands back his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs who was thus conducted at leaſt upon ſome hopes of advantage by it at the Court. And conveys her away with him, Accompany'd by her Coſen, and her Siſter, preſently going on to Attaque the Town of <hi>Carthens,</hi> which Siege held ſo long that it gave time enough to an
<note n="*" place="bottom">Iſabelle Babou <hi>Wife to the Marqueſs of</hi> Sourd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Franciſs <hi>of</hi> Eſcoubleau.</note> Aunt of Madammoiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>d'Eſtree</hi> to beſtow a Viſit upon her Neice, a ſubtle and diſcreet Woman, by whom ſhe was ſo well inſtructed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170822:18"/> that ſhe wholly ſubmitted the Royal Captive to her Devotion. And the Marqueſs of Sourdre, her Uncle was Created Governour of this Town as ſoon as taken by the King.</p>
            <p>The King thus in Love with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> is now eſſaying to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anul his Marriage with the <note n="*" place="bottom">The Queen of <hi>Nuvarr</hi> is <hi>Marguerite</hi> of <hi>Vallois</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> Siſter to <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, firſt Wife to <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth.</note> Queen of <hi>Navarr,</hi> a Princeſs not only of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction from, but Siſter to a King, yet alas! to Crown whoſe other Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues the valuable one of the Chaſte <hi>Luoretia,</hi> was too much wanting, for which they had been long ſince ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and the Royal Sinner betaken her ſelf to one of her <note n="*" place="bottom">The Queens Caſtle, was that of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſon</hi> in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergne.</hi>
               </note> Caſtles; a place not only by its Fortifications render'd Impregnable, but alſo by the advantages of its ſituation upon a high Mountain, and in a very cragged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170822:19"/> Country. This Queen gave out that ſhe was willing to comply with the King upon Terms, upon which they had agreed had not this new Amour not only interrupted the Treaty, but put an utter barr to any further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in it; the King fearing leaſt the diſſolution of this Marriage once effected, thoſe of his Servants that affected him, might be urgent with him to Marry again, which he could by no means endure; Being one that neither could nor would love any thing but his Miſtreſs, whom this would have much offended, her ſelf being (as before was intimated,) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted.</p>
            <p>During this, was depending the Match between <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Catherine d'Bourbon,</hi> the King's Siſter, was Wife to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> Duke of <hi>Barr,</hi> who dy'd at <hi>Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> in the year 1604.</note> 
               <hi>Catherine d'Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> the King's Siſter and the Count of <hi>Soiſons,</hi> to whom the King had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd her, but changing his mind, he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170822:19"/> reſolves to beſtow her upon * the Duke of <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> a Prince though young, yet in truth far ſubmitting to the other in point of Amiableneſs, and ſo very diſagreeable to the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and Fancy of the Princeſs, that ſhe could not forbare upon the ſight of him, to let him audibly underſtand, that ſhe could not love him; the Duke is not diſcourag'd with this, but perceiving the King of his ſide, cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to render her all the Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he could; and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the <note n="*" place="bottom">The Duke of <hi>Montpenſier</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Soiſons</hi> both of the Family of the <hi>Bourbons,</hi> Princes of the Blood.</note> Duke of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at this Sute, in which his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val was Patroniz'd and encourag'd by the King, withdraws himſelf to his Houſe.</p>
            <p>In the interim came Madam <hi>d'Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> to the Town of <hi>Diepe,</hi> wherein ſhe finds Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> (who is the late Madam <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> thus ſtyl'd
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170822:20"/> after her Marriage,) and conſeſſeth ſhe Eſteems her for the greatneſs of her Beauty not to be unworthy the Affection of her Brother; a thing for which ſhe had ſo much deteſted her before, and envy'd her, that if ſhe beheld her with a pleaſant look, it was with a viſible force put upon her ſelf. And Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle</hi> on the other ſide, not being able to diſpence with ſo inſufferable a Grandure in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to whom ſhe muſt always bare ſo profound a deference, often reproach'd the King with her coming. Whoſe only remedy was to be moving, (as his Affairs frequently call'd upon him to do) to another place, and to carry his Miſtreſs along with him; who now began in good earneſt to intereſt her ſelf in all Affairs; which indeed was not difficult for her to do, by the fore-mentioned Inſtrument her Aunt, with whom the Chancellour <note n="*" place="bottom">The Chancellour <hi>Chiverney,</hi> is <hi>Philip Hurault</hi> Earl of <hi>Chiverney.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verney</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170822:20"/> is in Love. See hence the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of ſo Great a Maſters example! how ſtrange is it that ſo Sage and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent a Man as this, ſhould not be able to reſiſt his Paſſion! but ſo it is, and the King willing that all the World ſhould be as much in Love as himſelf, was glad to ſee him fetter'd in the common Lott. At this time dy'd very Tragycally Madam <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> Mother to Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> who as ſhe had Infamouſly lived, ſo was ſhe juſtly inflicted with ſuch a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Still continu'd the Love betwixt <hi>Bellgard</hi> and Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle;</hi> of which the King had ſome ſuſpicion; but ſo ſlight as yet, that the leaſt ſhew of Kindneſs from her, made him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it as Criminal. But there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened an Accident, had like to have made it much more viſible. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at one of his Houſes, in order to a certain Enterprize on that ſide, and being gone the ſpace of three or four
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170822:21"/> leagues to that effect, Madam <hi>d'Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brielle</hi> ſtays by the way, pretending that ſhe was ill, whilſt <hi>Bellgard</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited a Journey to <hi>Mantes,</hi> which was not far off. But no ſooner was the King gone, but <hi>Arphure,</hi> the chief Confident amongſt the women of Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> (being one tht ſhe intruſted upon all occaſions) gave entrance to <hi>Bellgard</hi> into a little Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of which ſhe only had the Key, who had alſo admittance into the Chamber, as ſoon as her Miſtreſs had diſpos'd it into that order as ſhe thought fit. As they were together, came back the King, who though he could not find what he had ſought for, had like now to have found what he did not ſeek; All that could be done to prevent it, was to ſhut up <hi>Bellgard</hi> in the Cloſet of <hi>Arphure,</hi> which was at the Beds-head of Madam <hi>d'Gabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elle,</hi> a Window from which lookt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Garden; no ſooner did the King come in (having poſſibly ſome
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170822:21"/> item giv'n him of this buſineſs) but he call'd for <hi>Arphure</hi> for ſome of thoſe Sweetmeats, that ſhe kept in this Cloſet. But was anſwered by Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> that ſhe was not at home, and that ſhe had given her leave to go ſee ſome Relations of hers that was in the Town; notwithſtanding the King ſtill inſiſted that he reſolv'd to eat ſome of them, and that if <hi>Arphure</hi> was not to be found, or ſome other Perſon to open it, he would break o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Door, and forthwith ſtrikes it with his Feet. The ſurprize ſure is inexpreſſible theſe two Lovers muſt be in, to find themſelves ſo near a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery! But Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> if poſſible, will prevent it, and therefore feigns ſo great an illneſs in her Head, that noiſe would very much diſturb her, which yet doth not at all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the King from his reſolution. And <hi>Bellgard</hi> ſeeing there was no other remedy, leaps out of the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow into the Garden, from whence
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170822:22"/> though it was very high, he had the fortune to do himſelf little hurt by the fall.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Arphure</hi> (who had only hid her ſelf that ſhe might not open the Door) came in very hot (as if upon ſome haſty Summons ſhe had poſted from her Friends out of the Town, whom Madam <hi>Gabrielle</hi> had pretended ſhe had given her leave to go ſee) and ſatisfies the King with what he with ſo much impatiency demanded. Upon which <hi>Bellgard,</hi> (as before was hinted) having ſo fortunately made his eſcape, and the intreague being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered, the ſubtile <hi>Gabrielle</hi> a thouſand times reproaches the King with the unkindneſs of his action which ſhe tells him, ſhe believes was only to find ſome plauſible occaſion to break with her, as (his Humour changing,) he had done with thoſe that he had loved before, but that ſhe would prevent him by returning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to her Husband, whom his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170822:22"/> had caus'd her to abandon. I confeſs (ſaith ſhe) through that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Paſſion which for you, I have entertain'd, I have forgot both my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and my Duty, whilſt you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid me with moſt innumerable Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſstancies under colour of Suſpicion, for which I have not given you grown'd for ſo much as a Thought; and with this the Tears flow'd down her Cheeks. Upon which, ſo great was the diſorder of the Royal Lover, that he begg'd her Pardon not only for what he had done, but the falſe deluding Paſſion alſo prov'd ſo much the cure of his Jealouſie, that it was long before he entertain'd it again.</p>
            <p>During all this, the Enemies of the King was in poſſeſſion of the Town of <hi>Paris;</hi> In which ſo great and nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous was the Quality, that they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a Court in which ſeveral things paſſed that are worthy of our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170822:23"/>
            <p> The <note n="*" place="bottom">The Dutcheſs of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> was <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Lorrain</hi> the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (and <hi>Ann d'Eſt</hi> his Wife) Father to <hi>Charles d'Lorrain,</hi> Duke of <hi>Mayenne.</hi>
               </note> Dutcheſe of <hi>Montpenſier</hi> a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to one of the Princes of the Blood, and Siſter to the Duke of <hi>Mayen</hi> (Chief of that party which held the firſt rank againſt the King) omitted nothing that might tend to the advancement of the affairs of her Brother, or rather of his eldeſt Son (her Nephew) of the ſame Party, of whom ſhe had a very good opinion. This Lady loved a Gentleman of the King's Party, that was really as well, as in Repute, a gallant Man; yet ſhewing him all the kindneſs that the beſt aſſurance (with any reſerve of Modeſty) could admit of, ſtill he could not return it, having a Paſſion for her Neice (the Daughter of her eldeſt Brother) <note n="*" place="bottom">Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> was <hi>Louyſe Marguerite</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> Daughter to the aforeſaid <hi>Henry d'Lorrain,</hi> and <hi>Catherine</hi> of <hi>Cleves.</hi>
               </note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> a Lady under the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170822:23"/> Character of one of the Handſomeſt of thoſe times. But being one to whom the King (as in the entrance of this Hiſtory is ſignifi'd) had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſome hopes of Marriage as ſoon as he ſhould be free, out of a proſpect of thus preferring her ſelf to the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Bed, ſhe contemn'd all her other Lovers. Amongſt whom <note n="*" place="bottom">Lord of <hi>Guiry,</hi> who afterwards Married <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erette Hurault</hi> Daughter to the Chancellour <hi>d'Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rney.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Guiry</hi> (ſuch was the afore-nam'd Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) was the firſt that perceiv'd it. For having done all that he could think of to oblige her, even ſo far as to ſupply them with Proviſions in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> in the time of its greateſt neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he receiv'd from her ſo angry and apparently diſdainful a look, as gave an utter ſtop to his any-farther Vanity in aſpiring.</p>
            <p>Indeed all the more brisk Gentlemen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Army of the part of the Duke of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayen,</hi> as well as the King's, had no
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170822:24"/> leſs than a Paſſion for this Lady. For though her Mother and her ſelf had, as they thought, withdrawn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a very private receſs, yet ſo great a confluence of Admirers was there even to this place (through the attraction of this Beauty) that it might properly enough be ſtyl'd the Court of that Party; yet after all, not ſo much was her Beauty, but her Envy was more at her Competiton Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> not only becauſe ſhe really exceeded her in Beauty, but alſo in that her far more envy'd hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, her favour with the King; and therefore ſought all poſſible means to be reveng'd upon her.</p>
            <p>Now when the King (as befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hinted, had laid ſuch cloſe ſiege t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paris,</hi> where aſſaults were often mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on both ſides, with ſuch frequent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchanges of Sallies and Repulſes, Madam <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> appeared ſometimes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Walls. At ſuch times it was the ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Guiry</hi> always took his occaſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170822:24"/> inſinuate ſomething or other that ſhould ſignifie his Paſſion, though ſhe as often with an aſſumed ſtate, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at this time, appeared not to underſtand him, the King having now ſent for her Picture, (who was not yet ſo wholly embarqu'd in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>d'Eſtree,)</hi> and it was likewiſe believ'd that the Peace, and this Match would have been concluded together. So that (fluſh'd with theſe hopes) ſhe not only deſpis'd <hi>Guiry,</hi> but all her other Lovers.</p>
            <p>Excepting the happy <hi>Bellgard,</hi> for a Truce being made upon ſome Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for ſix hours, and the Ladies diverting themſelves upon the Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perts to which the Gentlemen of the Army came up to confer with their Acquaintance, and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to contemplate the famed Beauties of Madam <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> and <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> amongſt the reſt: The ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Dame that before had made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of defying all the World, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170822:25"/> upon the ſight of this Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, that ſhe could love ſomething elſe beſides a King. And <hi>Bellgard</hi> himſelf was ſo much enſnar'd and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd by her Charmes, that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got Madam <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> and all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oaths he had made of loving nothing but her, and wholly devoted himſelf to the preſent Object; and from that time forth, they began to love one another. How ſtrange are the effects of reſiſtleſs Paſſions? <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> being (as it is ſaid) only come hither to juſtifie himſelf to Madam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle and the Dutcheſs, concerning the imputation he was under of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty of the death of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> (which the Dutcheſs had believ'd him to have a ſhare in, and had vow'd him revenge for) the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falls in love with him, and he with the Daughter, who was not wholly obdurate to him, yet both kept their Fires ſecret enough, the one that ſhe might not give cauſe of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170822:25"/> to her Mother; and the other that he might not offend Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> who was too much the preſent prop and buttreſs of his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, for him to be willing to loſe. All that he could do in this little time, was by his Friends, to inform and ſatisfie the Dutcheſs of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in this Caſe; whoſe juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſo well receiv'd, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd the Dutcheſs (who could not but believe thoſe his execrable Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations he made upon himſelf) and caus'd her to relinquiſh her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Opinion; and to command Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> no more to accuſe him, who was not difficult to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded ſo to do; becauſe, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him to be Guilty, yet not being now free to condemn him, ſhe thought it more ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to her preſent Circumſtances to be credulous. <hi>Heu! Quid non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis amor?</hi> Omnipotent Love! What is it thou canſt not do, even to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170822:26"/> juſtifying of the greateſt Crimes?</p>
            <p>Every one return'd after the Truce was expir'd, and <hi>Bellgard</hi> amongſt the reſt, toſs'd with ten thouſand various Cogitations; he could not nor would not quit Madam <hi>d'Gabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elle,</hi> and his new Paſſion gave him a moſt reſiſtleſs Inquietude. In fine, he reſolves to love them both, to conſerve the one and not to relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh the other, and from this time ſeeks out means to pleaſe the Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who receiv'd his Letters and Meſſages ſo well, that there was ſoon a fair Intelligence betwixt them.</p>
            <p>At this time came the young Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> out of Priſon, in which he had been ever ſince the death of his Father; and <hi>Bellgard</hi> knowing him, takes an occaſion to ſend a Trumpet to viſit him, with Letters for the Dutcheſs; who was cunning enough privately to conveigh as much into the hands of the young Princeſs.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170822:26"/> His Letters was receiv'd by the Dutcheſs her ſelf very well; and the Princeſs, though ſhe had not an opportunity of ſpeaking to him now, yet intimated by Signs, that any thing of this nature was not Ungrateful to her from this Knight; with which the expecting <hi>Bellgard</hi> was not a little pleas'd.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the War conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd, and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of a Paſs-port to one of her Houſes, the King not only grants it, but likewiſe that ſhe may paſs through the ſame place where he himſelf was with all his Court; where the young Lady (pleas'd with this Voyage) hoped both that <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> might now find ſome means to ſpeak to her, and that ſhe might alſo have an opportunity to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the envy'd Beauty of her Rival, anſwer'd that Character that was given of it: And <hi>Bellgard</hi> (a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy for them to the Court; being
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170822:27"/> but a due Reſpect to Perſons of this Quality) takes occaſion to beg one of the King, (who was himſelf of too courteous a diſpoſition not to grant it) and of which, (by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that Rank which he held in the Court) he had the Commiſſion himſelf.</p>
            <p>Arriv'd, both the Dutcheſs and the young Princeſs, receiv'd a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Careſſes from the King, of which the former, could not refrain from commending the Beauty of Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> who yet thought ſhe found Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> too handſome for her liking, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> on the other ſide was ſurpris'd with the Beauty of her Rival; yet both concealing the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which they mutual had of each other, receiv'd one another with all the coldneſs that was conſiſtent with a due civility; and Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> as ſoon as ſhe had ſeen Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> turn'd her ſelf towards <hi>Bellgard,</hi> and ſaid, Truly I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170822:27"/> thought ſhe had been more handſom, to which <hi>Bellgard</hi> anſwered nothing, being too much taken with this Lady. Now the King, who knew well all Paſſions, and likewiſe thoſe of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (not unpractis'd in the affairs of Love) did not doubt but that this Chevalier, (as indeed it was true enough) only amuz'd and blinded the Dutcheſs, and us'd his pretended Addreſſes to her, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to facilitate his Acceſs to the young Princeſs, with whom he judg'd he was in Love: This Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion had theſe two effects; It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd the King's ſuſpicion that he had entertain'd of his being in Love with Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> and caus'd him to put an end to all farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns upon Madam <hi>d'Guiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all her little Intereſts, eſteem'd the affection of her Lover the Duke of <hi>Bellgard,</hi> took ſo narrow a ſcrutiny of his actions, that ſhe knew that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170822:28"/> he lov'd Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> and that he alſo was not hated by her; at which ſhe conceiv'd ſo ſtrong a jealouſie of Madam <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> that ſhe was under no ſmall pain to ſuppreſs it. With which the Princeſs (ſtill puſhing her on) was (not ill pleas'd) propoſing to her ſelf this Advantage by it, That if upon her departure from the Court, ſhe could not boaſt her ſelf of gaining any thing upon the King, yet ſhe might at leaſt triumph over his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>The next day they departed, the Dutcheſs having obtain'd of the King a Neutrality for the Houſe ſhe was to go to, to which <hi>Bellgard,</hi> (ſo much inflam'd by the attractions of the fair Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe)</hi> did not a little contribute; the King making no ſcruple to grant him all that in this nature he could deſire, as a Bait to lure him from his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> who was
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170822:28"/> ſo exceſſively enrag'd by her jealouſie of Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> that ſhe would not ſo much as bid adieu to either the Mother or the Daughter, feigning her ſelf ill, and not ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf to be ſeen all that day by any Perſon whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellgard</hi> and all the Court con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted theſe Ladies on their way ſo far as that they return'd not till the next day, when the incenſed <hi>Gabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elle</hi> beheld her Lover with ſo much fury in her Eyes, that it began to trouble him; And ſeeing the beloved Princeſs no more, the preſent Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject retook him again, to whom (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd by his Intereſt, as well as by loſing the fair <hi>Ideas</hi> of the abſent Beauty) he reſettled himſelf; curſing his former inconſtancy and indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> to whom her Life was of leſs value than her Love, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with this Knight, contrives a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170822:29"/> means to continue it by inſtating her Son in a Treaty with the King, (for which ſhe might eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her ſelf, the Favourite <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> would not be left out of the Commiſſion) and to make way for it, ſends advice of it to the King. Who deſirous that all his Subjects might return to their Allegian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> particular a Prince that was one of the Chiefs of the Adverſe Party, and of whom he had ſo great an Opinion, diſpatch'd <hi>Bellgard</hi> immediately to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her.</p>
            <p>To which Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd as much as poſſible, averring that <hi>Bellgard</hi> was not a Man of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and that the Mother (inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating the Paſſion that ſhe had for <hi>Bellgard,</hi> and probably ſuſpecting ſome contrivance now of the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſes in relation to it) might be more pleas'd with his Mediation than the Son; But in the end, the Duke of <hi>Neverrs,</hi> in kindneſs to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170822:29"/> 
               <hi>Bellgard,</hi> (a Perſon then amongſt the firſt of the King's Favourites) prevail'd upon her (to do pleaſure to <hi>Bellgard,</hi> whom he lov'd moſt extreamly) no longer to oppoſe it; And did no ſmall favour by this to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> For this Treaty not quickly concluding, and <hi>Paris</hi> ſoon afterwards being ſurrendred into the King's hands, the Love of <hi>Bell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard</hi> to his Siſter was of no ſmall import, (this Surrender ſo much infeebling the Enemy.) A kindneſs he had never receiv'd, unleſs from the Benevolent hands of the Duke of <hi>Nevers,</hi> who did all that this Knight deſir'd, and with ſo great a zeal (and this ſeconded by the active and co-operating heat of the Duke himſelf) that he put an end to an Affair, that all the World ſtood aſtoniſh'd to ſee ſo ſoon and ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagiouſly accompliſh'd.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170822:30"/>
            <p> Behold how the Affairs of this Court are carried on, and directed to ſuch ends as was the leaſt thought of by all, by very few known to be certainly in perſuit, only there was ſome diſcourſe of it indeed in the Court. The Duke upon his coming was very graciouſly receiv'd by the King, and likewiſe ſo well from his Siſter, that he commenced Servant to her from this time.</p>
            <p>At this time it was (the King being now gone to beſiege a Town that was yet on the Party of the Duke of <hi>Mayen)</hi> that Madam <hi>d'Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brielle</hi> was brought to Bed of a
<note n="*" place="bottom">The Son borne by Madam <hi>d'Gabrielle,</hi> upon which ſhe was made Marchioneſs of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> was afterwards the Duke <hi>Vendoſme.</hi>
               </note> Son; At which the King conceives ſo great a Joy, that he cauſeth her to quit her Name, and aſſume the Title of Marchioneſs of <hi>Beaufort.</hi> And began not to love her more becauſe his love was before ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170822:30"/> it could receive no augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but more to Eſteem her, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Reſpect her.</p>
            <p>Seeing her ſelf in this condition, ſhe began to ſearch out all means to hinder her Marriage, and to aſſume to her ſelf higher Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Her Councellour, her Aunt, Madam <hi>d'Sourdis,</hi> inſinuating into her, that ſhe might arrive to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Fortunes. And her Gallant the old Chancellour of <hi>Chiverney,</hi> gave her likewiſe uſeful Councels to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this end, which ſhe began in good earneſt to execute, making Friends for her ſupport, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing, and preferring thoſe that depended upon her, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her Friends to perſwade the Queen to break a Marriage, from which ſhe could expect nothing but much uneaſineſs and miſtruſt; But for this time could gain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon her Spirits: In the mean time there is a Reconciliation
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170822:31"/> twixt <hi>Bellgard</hi> and his Miſtreſs, (who had ſo ſtrong an inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Love him, and be Beloved of him, that ſhe help'd to deceive her ſelf even when ſhe knew he flattered her, for which cauſe he was the more induſtrious, ſeeing her now more Puiſſant than ever.</p>
            <p>The Siſter of the King, and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> hid now no more their Paſſion, and the Duke began to take ill <hi>Bellgard</hi>'s often Viſits to his Lodgings; (who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his Service for the new Marchioneſs of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> could not wholly relinquiſh his Amour with Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> his Siſter) the Duke taking notice of his frequent Viſits at his Lodgings, reſents it, and began to examine the cauſe, in ſo much that Madamoiſelle <hi>d'-Guiſe,</hi> who feared her Brother might make ſome Rumour of it abroad; gives Advertiſement of it to <hi>Bellgard,</hi> who a little pauſing upon it with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170822:31"/> himſelf, had recourſe to the Duke of <hi>Nevers</hi> for Advice. The Duke informs him of the moſt proper Expedient that in his preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances he could uſe; which was, That ſome diſtant Service might be allotted, in order to his remove from the King, to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> which (he adviſes) may be the Government of <hi>Province;</hi> and engageth himſelf to employ his Intereſt towards the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of it, if it ſhould not be oppoſed by the Marchioneſs of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Bellgard</hi> therefore (aſſured of his Friend) ſpeaketh of it to her, taking occaſion from the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſhe bore to this Prince, to tell her it was now ſo publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, that it was even come to the King's Ear, to which it gave ſuch offence, that in her own Juſtification ſhe ought at leaſt to ſollicite his remove to ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Service, which his Courage
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170822:32"/> rendred him ſo capable of for the King, and propos'd the Government of <hi>Province.</hi> In ſhort, he manag'd his Buſineſs with ſo good a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> was ſoon diſpatch'd for <hi>Province.</hi> But for what happen'd there, I muſt refer you to the Hiſtorians.</p>
            <p>The King's Siſter infeſted with this Accident, recurrs to another Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> a Man brave, though in his Age, and had acquir'd the Favour of the laſt King, being by him preferr'd to great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Dignities. This laſted till her Marriage with the Duke of <hi>Barr,</hi> to whom ſhe was ſoon after actually married, and conducted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his own Country. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Beaufort</hi> remaining for this time the ſole Miſtreſs of the Court.</p>
            <p>Now the Duke of <hi>Bellgard</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaſt his love to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe</hi> ſhould occaſion him to loſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170822:32"/> his firſt Miſtreſs, reſolves to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a good Correſpondency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, and ſeeing he could do what he pleas'd with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, he perſwades her ſince ſhe was likely to be Queen, it might advance him to a Station in which he might be more Serviceable to her, if he could eſpouſe Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>d'Guiſe;</hi> However, if ſhe could not approve of the Marriage it ſelf, yet the pretext of it would be a plauſible means to remove the King's Suſpicion, which he had already entertain'd, and into which it was more than probable he might again relaſpe; and farther told her, that the Suſpicion of the King was a great ſtop to his Preferment, and that whatſoever in appearance he might do, yet ſhe knew that his Heart was ſtill with her. In brief, he knew ſo well how to Cajole her, that ſhe reſolv'd to give Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> who
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170822:33"/> Was glad to obtain a good Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with a Perſon of her Quality, and ſo Engagingly deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf, that ſhe indear'd the Marchioneſs to ſo extraordinary a Kindneſs for her, that they not only dreſs'd every day alike, but was as it were, knit like Joynt-Twins inſeperably together.</p>
            <p>This blinded for a while the King, and diverted the Suſpicion that he began to have. But one of his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le d'Chambers having ſeen a Letter which <hi>Bellgard</hi> writ to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, which he had found one morning when ſhe was ill, upon her Twy-light, where <hi>Arphure</hi> had left it, not believing that any one ſhould have to do ſo early in the Room; he commanded him to have an Eye upon them; Which doing, (and believing like a good Servant, that his Maſter was eſpous'd to this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,) and imagining that he ſaw <hi>Bellgard</hi> one night entring in with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170822:33"/> her, he gives advice immediately of it to the King, who preſently ſends <hi>Praſlin,</hi> (the afterwards Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall of <hi>France,)</hi> one of the Captains of his Guard, to Sacrifice him in the Chamber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Praſlin</hi> was much ſurpriz'd at this Command, and the Love he had for them both, made it very ungrateful; but however he muſt go; He takes with him ſuch a number of the Guards as he thought fit that was walking in the Hall, takes ſo far a way about, and makes ſo much noiſe, that he found no body at his entrance into the Room, but Madam <hi>Beaufort</hi> alone, to whom he delivers his Meſſage. Who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo unwilling to ſurprize them, promiſes never to forget ſo great a Kindneſs; and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe</hi> that was alſo privy to this action, conceiv'd ſo good an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of him for it, that ſhe aſſiſted him in his progreſs to thoſe ſignal
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170822:34"/> Preferments, which he afterwards enjoy'd till his Death.</p>
            <p>Madam <hi>d'Beaufort</hi> in the interim, complains mightily of the Jealouſies of the King; at which the King, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be ſenſible of, and relent her wrong, promiſeth her that it ſhould be never the worſe with her for it. But ceaſes not a little to Reproach her with <hi>Bellgard</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which ſhe ſwore ſhe had not read, and juſtifi'd her ſelf (which was not very difficult to do) very well to the King. Though <hi>Bellgard</hi> himſelf found ſo ill a Treatment upon it, that he was forc'd to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent himſelf from the Court; and with no leſs a Condition, than that he ſhould never preſume to return again till he was Marry'd, and brought his Wife with him to the Court. The Duke of <hi>Nevers,</hi> his ſupporting Friend, was dead, and Madam <hi>d Beaufort,</hi> found it too ill taken when ſhe ſpoke for him,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170822:34"/> that his ſhorteſt and beſt courſe was to Obey what was Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though it was with the greateſt Regret.</p>
            <p>During this Voyage, a <note n="*" place="bottom">The Wife to the Conſtable of <hi>Montmorancy,</hi> was <hi>Louiſe</hi> of <hi>Budos,</hi> Vicount of <hi>Portes,</hi> and of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine d'Clermont.</hi>
               </note> Wife of the Conſtable of <hi>Montmorancy</hi>'s, whom he had lately Marry'd, came to the Court, a Lady who by the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, or perhaps rather novelty of her Beauty, attracted the Eyes and Hearts of the Men, and by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Envy of the Ladies, though (perhaps) through the natural height of her Temper, as well as of the exalted pre-eminency of her Place, regardleſs of both, ſhe as much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalu'd the hatred of the Ladies, as the addreſſes of the Men.</p>
            <p>The King alſo himſelf was a little touch'd, (for which I ſuppoſe the Marchioneſs will not pardon him)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170822:35"/> However it hinders him not from taking all the occaſions of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting his Affection to this new Beauty. Sacred and Inviolable is the Prerogative of Kings, and Unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, (eſpecially in that of Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom they pleaſe) and the Marchioneſs muſt not oppoſe it. Though Madam <hi>de Montmorancy</hi> ſuffers it more to excite Envy from the Ladies, than for any Pleaſure that ſhe could take in it, being not only lov'd, but ador'd by the Marqueſs of <hi>Biron,</hi> a Son of Mars, who had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd the greateſt Reputation for Arms of any one of his time. But oh Unhappy Fortune! the admired Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doth no ſooner, (as it were) ſhow her ſelf to the World, but ſhe goes out of it again in one of her Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds; yet leaving two ſuch fair Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of her Excellencies behind her,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170822:35"/> a <note n="*" place="bottom">The Son brought into the World by her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her death, was <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Montmorancy,</hi> the ſecond of that Name, Peer and Marſhall of <hi>France,</hi> and afterwards Beheaded at <hi>Thoulouſe</hi> in <hi>October</hi> 1632. and her Daughter <hi>Charlotte Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guerete Montmorancy,</hi> Wife to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> firſt Prince of the Blood, deceaſed 1646. who had Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the Princes of <hi>Conde</hi> and <hi>Conty</hi> and the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs of <hi>Longueville.</hi>
               </note> Son and a Daughter, made the World ſome competent Amends for the loſs of ſo incomparable a Perſon. But theſe I ſhall ſpeak more of elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, being deſirous now to finiſh the Hiſtory of the Marchioneſs of <hi>Beaufort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who during this interval had a <note n="*" place="bottom">Madam <hi>d'Beaufort</hi> her Daughter, was <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Henriette</hi> Legitimate of <hi>France,</hi> Married 1619. to <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> Duke of <hi>Elbeuf,</hi> of whom ſhe had diverſe Iſſue, and the Son ſhe had ſoon after upon the diſanulling of her Marriage, was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander Vendoſme</hi> Grand Prior of <hi>France,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards dy'd Priſoner in the Caſtle of <hi>Vincennes.</hi>
               </note> Daughter, and not long after a Son, but the laſt of theſe, after the nullifying of her Marriage. Which ſo much elevated the Marchioneſs,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170822:36"/> that ſhe left no ſtone unturn'd to bring to paſs her Marriage with the King. Who now more Amourous than ever, upon the Birth of theſe two Sons, gratifi'd her in all that ſhe could deſire, removing one of the Greateſt of his Council, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to thwart this deſign. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he could obtain the Conſent of his Queen, and that there wanted nothing more but the Concurrence of the Pope to ratifie the diſſolution of his former Marriage, which was the only Obſtacle of this. To which purpoſe <hi>Hilery</hi> is diſpatch'd to <hi>Rome,</hi> the ableſt Man of his Council, and deſiring nothing more than to Oblige both the King and his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>A little before this, the King had made her Dutcheſs; in which Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Place ſhe ſo well behav'd her ſelf, that though ſhe could not be by all belov'd, yet ſhe was hated by none; and growing Big again, demean'd her ſelf with ſo much Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170822:36"/> Circumſpection, and ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute a Chaſtity, that ſhe conſorted only with the Veſtals, and in both Dreſs and Actions demonſtrated ſo perfect a Modeſty, that the King remembred with regret that ever he had ſuſpected her; and was mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted down into the moſt invincible reſolution to make her his Wife.</p>
            <p>At this time <hi>Buſſy Lamet,</hi> an old Courtier of no ſmall Account and Eſteem with the King, (both to Oblige the Marchioneſs, and to Incite the King by his Example) Marries a Miſtreſs of his by whom he had had ſeveral Children; which was of no ſmall moment to the Marchioneſs, for we are all not ill pleas'd with-parallel Inſtances, (to render them the leſs culpable) when our Actions are otherwiſe not ſo juſtifiable in themſelves.</p>
            <p>Commands were now given to the Ambaſſadour at <hi>Rome,</hi> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the Diſſolution of the Marriage,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170822:37"/> and to ſolicite the Conſent of the Queen, which was rendred the more Urgent by the Marchioneſs, becauſe being with Child, and near her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, ſhe was very unwilling that the Birth ſhe went with ſhould be Illegitimate; Who to make publick profeſſion of her Faith, Celebrates her <hi>Eaſter</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> Lodging in the Cloiſter of St. <hi>Germain L'Auxerrois;</hi> On Holy <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> ſhe was at Service, at a Church in the end of the Town, call'd the <hi>Tenebris,</hi> which they perform'd very Harmoniouſly; ſhe went her ſelf in a Litter, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Captain of the Guards, but the Princeſſes in Coaches; and leaſt ſhe might be either too much crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or obſerv'd, her Chapel was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe cleared by the Captain of the Guards. Where during the time of the Office, ſhe entertain'd her ſelf, and Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> who was with her, with Letters from <hi>Rome,</hi> by which ſhe was ſatisfi'd that her
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170822:37"/> Deſires ſhould ſoon be accompliſh'd, and alſo from the King himſelf, intimating him ſo impatient to ſee her Queen, that he had remanded <hi>du Froſne,</hi> one of his Secretaries of State (a Perſon who becauſe related to her in Marriage, muſt needs be wholly devoted to her Intereſt) to <hi>Rome;</hi> to urge and preſs his Holineſs to a permiſſion of what he was ſo much reſolved to do; and in ſuch Prayers as theſe was the time of Devotion ſpent, But ended, the Marchioneſs, (who had gave Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> to Underſtand that ſhe was going to Bed, and had deſir'd the diverſion of her Company,) immediately betakes her ſelf to her Litter; and Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> to her Coach, cauſing her ſelf to be ſet down at the Dutcheſſes.</p>
            <p>Whom (arriv'd) ſhe found not only undreſs'd, but in great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with her Head; and ſoon after ſhe falls into a ſtrong Convulſion,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170822:38"/> yet out of which by ſtrength of Remedies ſhe was recover'd; and upon this would have writ to the King, had ſhe not been reattack'd and prevented by a ſecond Fit, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which receiving a Letter from the King, ſhe attempted alſo to read it, and was again retaken by a third, ſo that in the end encreaſing mightily upon her, and overpower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unequal ſtrength of her Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they put too certain a period to her Life. On <hi>Wedneſdey</hi> night this Illneſs firſt took her, and on <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> deliver'd by the force of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, ſhe Dy'd on <hi>Saturday</hi> in the Evening, devoid of all Senſe, as far as any body could perceive.</p>
            <p>The King who was now at one of his Houſes, was early enough advertis'd of this Sickneſs, but imagining it to be only the reſult and diſorder of Breeding, was not much mov'd with it at the firſt. But the Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day-Meſſenger bringing him News
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170822:38"/> both of its Danger and Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, he caus'd him to make to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Paris;</hi> who coming within ſix leagues of it. (where he found all the Lords of his Court) they gave him to underſtand by the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Countenances, that his Miſtreſs was dead; who after he had read the too fatal certainty of it in their looks and geſtures, was mightily Troubled, and required ſolitude, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſing all his Attendance, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Buſſy Lamet,</hi> (the Perſon before ſpoken of) and the Duke of <hi>Retz,</hi> who had the Character of being extream good Company; the laſt of theſe (giving him firſt a little time to vent his Paſſion) told the King, almoſt ſmiling, that (in his Opinion) he was very happy, and that weighing of his preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, muſt needs induce him to believe it; and that the Gods had favour'd him by her death: The Royal concern was too great
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170822:39"/> at firſt to be laid by ſuch Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, but the King a little reviving, and calling to mind the Important Buſineſs he was about, (which was intimated by the Duke) he confeſs'd what he had ſaid to be true, and lifting up, his Eyes to Heaven (not inſenſible both of this and all his other Mercies) makes ſuitable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to that Beneficent Hand from which he had receiv'd them, and ſo well contented himſelf, that within the ſpace of ſeaven weeks he became Enamour'd of Madam <note n="*" place="bottom">Madam <hi>d'Antragues,</hi> the afterwards Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Verneuil,</hi> was <hi>Henriette</hi> of <hi>Balſac d'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Antragues,</hi> Siſter to <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Vallois</hi> Earl of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vergne,</hi> afterwards Duke of <hi>Angouleſme,</hi> Natural Son to <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>d'Antragues,</hi> (the afterwards Marchioneſs of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neail)</hi> both very Young and Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and of a good Houſe, and if not equalling the other in Beauty, yet exceeding her in Gayety, and ſo
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170822:39"/> well ſupplying her abſence, that ſhe (at the leaſt) ſtrook out all his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly Reflections upon her death.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of State now ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ambitious Marchioneſs thus ſtopp'd and controwl'd by Fate in her purſuit after Majeſty and the iminent danger that in this reſpect they was deliver'd from, by her death, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to prevent the ſame danger from this new Beauty, (whoſe height of Spirit they knew not to be inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to the others) and therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditiouſly puſh'd on the King to Marriage, and he that was at <hi>Rome</hi> to mediate for it with the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> now mediates for it with the Princeſs of
<note n="*" place="bottom">The Princeſs of <hi>Florence</hi> was <hi>Marie d'Medicis</hi> Daughter to <hi>Francis d'Medicis,</hi> great Duke of <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cany</hi> and <hi>Jane</hi> Arch Dutcheſs of <hi>Auſtria</hi> by her Birth Queen of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Florence.</hi> To whom the Pope not only gave all his neceſſary conſent, but likewiſe the Queen <hi>Margaret</hi> all that Was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170822:40"/> from her; inſomuch that the buſineſs was ſoon concluded that ſo it anticipated both the Imagination of the King, and knowledg of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, who was now big, and conveigh'd in order to her lying down, to one of the Houſes of the King, towards which he conducted her with very good hopes, but get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome hurt by the way ſhe prov'd Abortive and was very ill; though through the aſſiſtance of the King, and the concurrance of all imaginable Remedies, ſhe came again to her health. It was at this time that ſhe heard that the Match was agreed upon betwixt the King and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Florence,</hi> upon which ſhe ſo impetuouſly taunted at the Amorous Prince that he had much adoe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce her to a good humour. And <hi>Bellgard</hi> (whom ſhe ſuſpected to be the cauſe of all this) for her not having given him that reception which he had formerly had with
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170822:40"/> the Marchioneſs of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> (and would have had with her) ſhe is reſolv'd to be reveng'd upon by the Prince of <hi>Joinville,</hi> (the afterwards Duke of <hi>Chevreus)</hi> a Prince Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and Young, and of a good Grace, and one of her Admirers, whom ſhe cauſeth to attempt his Life one night at his entrance into the Houſe of one <hi>Sebaſtien Zamet</hi> (with whom the King then Supp'd) there encountering him with his Sword. <hi>Bellgard</hi> was wounded, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſeeing it, purſu'd the Prince of <hi>Joinville,</hi> whom they had certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kill'd had it not been for the interpoſing of <hi>Rambouillett,</hi> a young Chevalier of a good Houſe, who was ſo much wounded in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, that it was believ'd he would have dy'd.</p>
            <p>So o'erflow'd the King with Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler at this Action, that he would
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170822:41"/> not only have puniſh'd the Prince, but have permitted the other to dye on his Wounds. Notwithſtanding he was ſo well lookt to by ſtealth, that he eſcap'd, and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (Mother to the Prince) and his Siſter; obteyn'd his reconciliation with the King, tho both (much offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at this action,) ſuſpected that the Prince had no other cauſe to treat <hi>Belgard</hi> in this faſhion but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his love to the Marchioneſs of <hi>Vernucil;</hi> thus all was ſoon appeas'd, and a motion of War made upon the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> on the account of the Marquiſate of <hi>Saluſſes;</hi> which he had treacherouſly ſeiz'd upon and taken during the diverſion of the laſt King at <hi>Blois.</hi> For the King who by dint of Battle had recover'd all the reſt of his Kingdom, and inſtated himſelf in the hereditary ſeat of his Royal Anceſtors, could not bear that the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> in competition
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170822:41"/> with him ſo petty a Prince, ſhould pretend to exclude him from a Country that was his own due, and proper inheritance, which he had often demanded, and which the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſtood poſſeſs'd of, by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means but that of a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neighbourly and unjuſt ſurpriſe and fraudulent uſurpation. And the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> was now come, in order to ſome accommodation betwixt the King and himſelf, thinking poſſibly to render his deſigns more effectual, by being preſent in his own perſon. But indeed his chief dependence was upon the intelligence he had with the deceaſed Dutcheſs, in whoſe life-time he had aſſur'd the King of his intention to wait upon him, and had ſo much ingag'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by both what he writ and what he ſaid, that there was now no room for a retreat. At his coming there was nothing but feaſting and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170822:42"/> gallantry in the Court, and ſuch as was argumentative of a general ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he makes Preſents to all the handſome and principal Ladies of the Court, and it may be a little more than was for the benefit of ſome of them; and now the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies (as upon ſuch occaſions) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting for Precedency, and the King not determining the point, there oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd a moſt pleaſant Diverſion both to the King and the Marchioneſs.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> return'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing any thing, and the King reſolved to make War upon him; which, as he goes to receive his Queen, the Princeſs of <hi>Florence Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria d'Medicis,</hi> (that Country lying in his way) he performed. Which (and which was ſoon) being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du'd, the Pope intermediates for an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation, and the King receives his Queen, whom he had before Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous'd by his deputed Proxy, his Uncle
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170822:42"/> (having before ſent to him his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curation by <hi>Bellgard,</hi> which much augmented the hatred of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs;) And thus his Majeſty obtain'd his deſire.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Marri'd Queen, was come as far as <hi>Marſeille</hi> to meet the King, thither conducted by his Aunt the Dutcheſs (of the Houſe of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſins,)</hi> and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Mantoue</hi> her Siſter, and <hi>Eleonor d'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Medicis</hi> her Couſin German, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon much eſteem'd in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> (and who had been much enamour'd of this Princeſs before ſhe was Queen) and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceiv'd by two Cardinals, the Conſtable, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> that was Governour of the Province. By the Princeſſes Dowagers of <hi>Nemours</hi> and <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and many other Ladies, the Marchioneſs of <hi>Guercheville</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, whom the King had lov'd, and (finding perhaps more
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170822:43"/> Vertuous than he deſir'd) had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to make Maid of Honour to his Queen; keeping his Word with her after the end of ten Years, it being ſo long ſince he firſt lov'd her.</p>
            <p>The Queen was brought on with all ſorts of Magnificence to the Town of <hi>Lyons,</hi> where ſhe was expected by the King; and the Nuptial Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies perform'd: The two Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Conſtable, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Vantadour,</hi> and the Counteſs of <hi>Auvergne,</hi> the afterwards Dutcheſs of <hi>Angouleſme,</hi> being here; both very Handſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the firſt belov'd of <hi>Eleonor d'Medicis,</hi> who (as before ſaid) was under the Repute of ſuch a Gallant Man; but his Love as vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile as he, ſtay'd no longer with him than he at the Court.</p>
            <p>Though it is otherways with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> betwixt whom the quarrel was ſo great, that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170822:43"/> it divided the whole Court; though at laſt reconcil'd by the King, and without doubt not without ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention himſelf upon the Dutcheſs of <hi>Vantadour;</hi> yet notwithſtanding he relinquiſheth not his Amour with the Marchioneſs of <hi>Verneuile,</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding daily his Meſſengers to her; who now ceaſetho not to treat the Queen even after her own inventions, and there wanted not thoſe that made Report of it to the Queen, which made ſo great a broil, that it almoſt embaras'd in it the whole Court; ſome reporting things to the Queen; others to the Marchioneſs; the firſt, that they might inſinuate themſelves into the favour of the Queen; and the latter, that they might engage the Marchioneſs; and how many others there might be (He only knows that knows all things) that only to render the breach ſo much
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170822:44"/> the more wide and incurable, might act on both ſides.</p>
            <p>Theſe Feuds did not preſently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, but during the Queens Voyage to <hi>Paris,</hi> there was another Intreague that amuſed the Court; the King having ſent, with Madamoiſelle, to the Queen, the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nemours,</hi> as Governeſs of her Houſhold, the Marchioneſs of <hi>Guercheville,</hi> as Maid of Honour, and Madam <hi>d'Ritchelieu</hi> as Lady of the Attire; the Queen refus'd the laſt, ſaying, that ſhe had <hi>Leonora</hi> already in the Place, who had not only all along ſerv'd her, but whom ſhe had now brought Over on purpoſe for that Place; to which the King reply'd, that having given it to Madam <hi>d'Ritchelieu,</hi> ſhe was deſirous of that Office; in ſo much that this made an abſolute Rupture betwixt the Marchioneſs and the Queen, and the whole Retinue that was ſent her was remanded back
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170822:44"/> again to the King. The Sagacious Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> ſoon knew what Profit ſhe might reap from this occaſion, and takes part incontinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Queen, gaining by it a particular account and favour with her: The ſame day ſhe arriv'd at <hi>Paris,</hi> the King Commanded the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nemours</hi> to fetch the Marchioneſs of <hi>Verneuil,</hi> and preſent her to the Queen, which the wary Princeſs declining, would fain have excus'd her ſelf from, ſaying, That by ſo doing, ſhe ſhould loſe all her Credit with her Miſtreſs; but the King, contrary to his Cuſtom, (which was always to be Courteous) Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding her ſomething ruffly to do it, ſhe Obey'd. But the Queen aſtoniſht at ſuch a ſurprize, receiv'd the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs very coldly, who notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being of a Nature well aſſur'd, addreſs'd her ſo familiarly, and with ſuch freedom and talkativeneſs, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170822:45"/> ſhe compell'd her in the end to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain her. The Dutcheſs in the interim that introduc'd her, received little ſatisfaction upon it from the King, and a very bad Countenance from the Queen, who was ſo much irritated by this action, as never after to forget it; and <hi>Leonora</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving by this, that ſhe was not ſecure in her Place, without the Approbation of the King, ſollicited the Marchioneſs to be her Friend, promiſing her, that if ſhe could ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Royal Approbation, ſhe would put her into a capacity of doing what ſhe pleas'd with the Queen. Which the Marchioneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, ſo well effected, that the ſmiles of Majeſty attended it, it much mittigating the former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency of the Queen, which the King obſerving, and being weary of his Stages to the Marchioneſs two or three times in the day, cauſed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170822:45"/> Lodgings to be prepar'd for her in the <hi>Louvre,</hi> and brings her thither, which after ſome little time rekin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'led again the jealouſie of the Queen, ſhe being ever and anon entertain'd by ſeveral hands, with the diſcourſes of the Marchioneſs, which favour'd of ſo little reſpect, that it began to make a breach of that Intelligence that was betwixt them; Both theſe was Big together, and it was no ſmall difficulty for the King ſo to accommodate himſelf to them both, that neither might be diſoblig'd, the Queen he was to treat with all the reſpect due to her Quality, and he delighted more in the company of the Marchioneſs. Every one alſo that would not diſpleaſe the King, reſorted to her, which the Queen took very ill, and indeed, ſo near were their Lodgings, and ſo much within each others inſpection, that it prov'd the cauſe of perpetual dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170822:46"/> betwixt them. In the mean time <hi>Leonora,</hi> by Preſents; kept her correſpondence with the Marchioneſs, not queſtioning but it might conſiſt with a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding with her Miſtreſs, the Charm only of whoſe favour (it ſeems) having very few other Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, had procured her a Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, a certain Gentleman of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> that came along with the Queen, who now made his court, and was ſo fortunate to be approv'd; His Name was <hi>Conchini,</hi> of good Extraction, and therefore <hi>Leonora,</hi> who her ſelf proceeded from the ſcum of the People, thought him no ill Choice; but yet there was ſome difficulty before this Marriage could come to paſs, for the King did not love him, and thoſe of the Houſe of the Queen hated him, and the Queen her ſelf fear'd to ſpeak of it, left it ſhould be refus'd. In
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170822:46"/> fine, conſulting together, they made recourſe to her Omnipotency the Marchioneſs of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo well in it, that he obtain'd the freedom of being with her as often as he pleas'd. With which the Marchioneſs her ſelf was not ill ſatisfi'd, knowing that by this ſhe oblig'd <hi>Leonora,</hi> and through her the Queen, whoſe favour, though ſhe did not ſo much reſpect, yet ſhe valu'd her Reſent ments.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Conchini</hi> had had this acceſs to <hi>Leonora,</hi> he makes his Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that he might Marry her. The Dutcheſs makes ſome difficulty of it at the firſt, knowing the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the King to theſe two Perſons, but in the end, through the Interceſſion likewiſe of <hi>Leonora,</hi> who engag'd that the Queen ſhould ſpeak of it too, ſhe took up a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of cauſing this Marriage to ſucceed; the Queen ſends daily to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170822:47"/> her Lodgings, to know the News, makes her half the Preſents ſhe receives, and treats her better than either of the Princeſſes. But before this Match is accompliſh'd, the Queen and Marchioneſs are to be in the Straw.</p>
            <p>The Queen is firſt, and preſents the World with the moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Happy Prince <hi>Louis,</hi> Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin the Thirteenth; and a Month after the Marchioneſs brings to light Prince <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bourbon,</hi> (afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Matz)</hi> both of which are welcom'd into the World with the greateſt Joy, which continu'd all the Winter; and Perparations are made by the Queen, for the ſpace of three months, for a Ball, in which the Marchioneſs had a part, which ſo pleas'd the King, that he conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Marriage of <hi>Conchini</hi> and <hi>Leonora;</hi> and that the Queen might not only beſtow her in Marriage,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170822:47"/> but that ſhe might alſo give her ſuch fortune, as might comport with the quality of her place. The good intelligence laſted all the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and part of the next Summer, but the Court is impatient of too long a Calm, and every one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth himſelf ſome advantage from change and competitions.</p>
            <p>The King a little before, had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of <note n="*" place="bottom">Madam <hi>d'Villars</hi> the Kings Miſtreſs, after the Deceaſe of her Siſter the Dutcheſs of <hi>Beaufort</hi> is the ſame was hinted before the Marchioneſs of <hi>Villars</hi> or <hi>Ceriſay.</hi>
               </note> Madam <hi>d'Villars</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Dutcheſs of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> who indeed had no other Beauty but that of her Youth and her Haire. This Lady envy'd the Marchioneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly, in that ſhe had (as ſhe thought) raviſh'd from her the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the King, and as ſhe was malicious, ſo ſhe began to put her
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170822:48"/> Malice into practice; revealing to the Queen her intentions, whom ſhe knew to be grown weary of the audaciouſneſs of the Marchioneſs, and not unlikely to favour her deſigns, which ſhe did, and neither <hi>Leonora,</hi> nor <hi>Conchini,</hi> diſcover'd any thing of the intreague; the firſt of theſe being but ſeldom with the Queen, and the laſt ſitting down by his preſent fortune was not inquiſitive into the affair. I have otherwhere ſaid, that the Prince of <hi>Joynville,</hi> was a long time in Love with the Marchioneſs of <hi>Vernuielle,</hi> and now he becomes enamour'd of Madam <hi>d'Villers,</hi> who was ſo ſubtle and knew ſo well how to perſwade him, that ſhe got from him the Letters the Marchioneſs had writ to him, during that Amour, in which ſhe had fawn'd officiouſly upon him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly treated both the King and the Queen, who upon the ſight
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170822:48"/> of them, (though ſhe beheld them with the diſdain they deſerv'd) could not refrain from letting her know ſhe was pleas'd, and perſwaded her to ſhow them to the King, At firſt ſhe could not conſent knowing the great credit of the Marchioneſs with the King, and fearing her ſpirit, but in the end is prevail'd upon by the perſwaſions of the Queen. Whilſt Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> that introduc'd her to the Queen (not withſtanding the vivacity of her Wit) could not diſcover at the firſt what ſhould be the eauſe that ſhe ſhould be in ſo particular a grace with the Queen that carried it ſo coldly to all the reſt of the World; being a thing (ſhe thought) too intricate to ſalve. And indeed they induſtriouſly hid the matter from her, becauſe it tended ſo much towards the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of her Brother. After the Train had been laid for ſome
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170822:49"/> days, and contriv'd ſo well, that the ill, malicious Work, might be done with ſome ſecurity, and the plotted miſchief effectually accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd; Fire is to be given, and the Marchioneſs, if poſſible, to be blown up, taking then the King at an advantage, Madam <hi>d'Villars</hi> ſhows him, perhaps, what he was not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſee, the aforeſaid Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Marchioneſſes Infidelity and Deſpight, and thus the ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd Syren accoſted him;
<q>Royal Sir, The Obligations I am under to Your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nty, and the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I always entertain'd for ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Perſonage as your Self, would not ſuffer me any longer to conceal the Indignities offered You: You, who are, or ought to be, the Maſter of others, and not ſure, their Scorn and Contempt, and one of the moſt deſerving Men in the World.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170822:49"/>
            <p> This good Prince, who eaſily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf to be flatter'd, and gave no unwilling Ear when they inſiſted, eſpecially, upon his merit, (which I ſuppoſe) the ſubtle Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite well enough underſtood, thank'd her for her Intelligence ſhe had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, and ſo unutterably ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs the unworthy uſage he has had, that he ſends immediately one of his Confidents to Reproach the Marchioneſs with her unfaithfulneſs, proteſting that ſhe ſhould never ſee his Face again.</p>
            <p>She was not at this time at her Lodgings in the <hi>Louvre,</hi> but in the Town, where ſhe was much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd with this News; but in the midſt of this Diſorder ſo well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded her ſelf, and conſerv'd ſo much reſpect for the Perſon that ſent it, that ſhe reply'd after this manner, with much temper.
<q>As
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170822:50"/> I have never done any thing yet, (I am aſſur'd) to offend the King, ſo I cannot divine the Reaſons for which he ſhould thus uſe me, and I hope the Truth coming to light, will ſufficiently revenge me of thoſe that have made theſe falſe Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon him.</q> And with this retir'd into her Cloſſer, where ſhe gave that ſcope to the exceſſive trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon her Spirits, which ſhe thought was not diſcreet to do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Bellgard</hi> having learn'd this Intreague, gives notice of it to Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe,</hi> who though ſhe did not love the Prince, yet he foreſaw the diſpleaſure it would give to his Siſter, if it ſhould not be remedy'd, and therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives a way, which was this.</p>
            <p>A Secretary of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>'s
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170822:50"/> counterfeiting in perfection all ſorts of Hands, it is reſolv'd that the Prince of <hi>Joynville,</hi> (amourous of Madam <hi>d'Villars</hi> as before) ſhould affirm that the Secretary by his Art having got ſome Writings of the Marchioneſſes, imitated them ſo well, that the Prince himſelf and Madam <hi>d'Villars,</hi> with whom he was in Love, and who mortally hated the Marchioneſs, combin'd together by his skill, to counterfeit thoſe Letters on purpoſe to undermine her, which the Marchioneſs underſtanding ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded ſo well, that ſhe reingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated her ſelf with the King, and rendred him ſuch reaſons for the Credibility of this Aſſertion, that ſhe totally proſelited him to its Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; and though his Prejudice at the firſt was not ſo eaſie to allay, yet at laſt he yielded himſelf van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd; as much poſſibly by his own inclination to think well
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170822:51"/> her, as by the ſmooth coercion of her Tongue.</p>
            <p>But the Prince of <hi>Joinville</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever (not withſtanding the Subtlety of this evaſion) is commanded away into <hi>Hungary;</hi> where the <hi>Turk</hi> was making War; Madam <hi>d'Villars</hi> to her Houſe, and the Secretary to Priſon; ſee hence the conſequence of intermedling, Madam <hi>d'Villars</hi> meets the due reward of her Actions, and is diſmiſt with ſhame to her Houſe, and hath created to herſelf a great and powerful Enemy.</p>
            <p>During theſe bickerings and hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leburlies, the Queen's hatred to the Marchioneſs was more conſpicuous, for thinking her now to be almoſt ruin'd ſhe doth her utmoſt to ruin her quite, and is daily huing at what ſhe thinks is already declining, her Fortune, to which the ill offices ſtill
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170822:51"/> daily render'd her by the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, do more exaſperate her, who is always pecking at the Favourites of the Queen, and the Queen on the other ſide deteſting thoſe that are her Creatures; but behold another occurrence.</p>
            <p>The King is advis'd of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſſes keeping a Correſpondence with <hi>Spain,</hi> and it went ſo far that ſhe was Arreſted for it, and the Earl of <hi>Auvergne</hi> her Brother; but ſince you have a farther relation of theſe Things amongſt the Hiſtorians, I ſhall ſay no more but that Madam <hi>Villars</hi> and her Lover was again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call'd upon it.</p>
            <p>It hap'ned now at this time that the King became enamour'd of a fair Lady whom he Marry'd quickly after, the Counteſs of <hi>Eſtanges,</hi> and a little after this, another far more
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170822:52"/> beautiful, whom he alſo Marry'd to draw her from the place in which ſhe was, agreeing with her Conſort that Marry'd her, that he ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon her the ſame Night after the Cerimony was perform'd.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Marchioneſs obtain'd the Royal Grace, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from her Priſon, to her Houſe at <hi>Vernueil,</hi> the King was pleas'd with his new Miſtreſs, and it was very calm Weather with the Court; the King alſo at this time Marryed Madamoiſelle <hi>d'Guiſe</hi> to a Prince of the Blood Royal, with whom the Queen gave, what was neither beneath her own Quality to give or the others to receive.</p>
            <p>The King ſeeing again the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Vernueil,</hi> had a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to her, yet kept it ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, that it was long before it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170822:52"/> came to the Queens knowledg, but as ſoon as ſhe knew it ſhe was ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled, and abſolutely forbid all ſuch Perſons any acceſs to her, that ſhould at any time viſit the Marchioneſs, under the pain of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing driven from her preſence; which the King took ill, but yet was forc'd to bare with it, a little after the King (a never failing Gallant) becomes Enamour'd of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nevers,</hi> a Princeſs of great Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that very much honour'd his perſon, but had no great eſteem for his paſſion. This ſeaſon hapned commodiouſly for the Kings deſigns, for the King intending to Chriſten the young Prince's his Sons, had invited the Dutcheſs of <hi>Mantoue</hi> to be Godmother to the Eldeſt.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170822:53"/>
            <p> This Princeſs was Siſter to the Queen, and her Husband a near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Duke of <hi>Neverrs,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he obliged the Dutcheſs of <hi>Nevers</hi> to ſtay longer than uſual at the Court, (to give oppertunity to the King to purſue his Amour) the King ſeeking all occaſions to ſpeak to her, whilſt ſhe on the other hand avoided it as much as poſſible, waving it to the very utmoſt limits of a due reſpect; in the end the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies being perform'd, the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Nevers</hi> without ſo much as bidding adieu retir'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Court, the latter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving never again to return; the Duke, being ſoon after employ'd as Envoy to <hi>Rome,</hi> went herſelf along with him thither, and oblig'd the King to diſpoſſeſs himſelf of a fancy, that not only prov'd fruitleſs, but very troubleſome to him; being not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170822:53"/> accuſtom'd to the difficulties he found in this Amour. This Voyage endur'd above a Year; and the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs at her return came to do reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Queen, the King being then with her. Upon which the King beholding her with a bended brow, let her know aloud that he thought ſhe was extreamly chang'd; but the Dutcheſs taking no notice at all of it, continu'd ſtill to deport herſelf in the ſame manner, and to ſpend the reſt of her life, in all the modeſty that could become, or was requiſite in an excellent and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Woman.</p>
            <p>The King by this was again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to the Marchioneſs, <hi>d'Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueil,</hi> which the Queen ſo impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently bore, that notwithſtanding all the endeavours of the Council to prevent them, and to ſhow how diſagreeable they was to Majeſty,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170822:54"/> it fomented moſt extream differences betwixt them: And now there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd a very ſurpriſing accident, that made much noiſe, and indeed was very ſtrange, the King and Queen going to a houſe of theirs near <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> on the other ſide the River <hi>Sein,</hi> they was obliged to paſs it in the <note n="*" place="bottom">The Ferry ſpoken of in which the King and Queen paſs'd the River <hi>Sien,</hi> overturning, was the cauſe of a Bridge being ſoon after built over that River.</note> Ferry, the Coach with theſe two in it, accompany'd only with the Princeſs <hi>de Conty,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> by ſome accident or other, was overturn'd before it came to the Shore; the King and Duke eſcaping very well, leaping ſoon enough out of the Coach; but the Ladies ran ſome hazard, and drank a little more than they deſir'd, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ambitious Element ſquench'd its thirſt a little too much upon the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170822:54"/> Ladies. Some few days after the King going to Viſit the Marchioneſs of <hi>Vernueil,</hi> ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doles him for the unhappy chance, and tells him ſhe was in great pain for him, but if ſhe had been preſent, and had ſeen the King leaping ſafe out of the Coach, ſhe ſhould have had the civility to have ſaid let the Queen drink, (a ſaying it ſeems us'd upon the Ceremony of chooſing King and Queen, which ſhe wittily made uſe of upon this occaſion) which when the Queen came to hear, ſhe flew out into ſo great and implacable a rage, that ſhe was fifteen days without changing ſo much as one word with the King, ſo that Perſons of great Figure and Quality was forc'd to interpoſe to qualifie her Reſentments; in the end the accord was made,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170822:55"/> and there muſt be a Ball to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt it, wherein the Queen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to give her ſelf the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of having a part. But it is unhappily interrupted, for the King inſiſting upon the reception of the Counteſs of <hi>Morett</hi> alſo into it, and the Queen oppoſing and refuſing it, it made ſuch a rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture betwixt them, that it broke off the Ball; (This Counteſs of <hi>Morett</hi> is the Lady that I before ſaid, was quitted of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.)</p>
            <p>Who was now lov'd by the Prince <hi>d'Joinville,</hi> whom ſhe did not ill entertain, but the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs is, it comes to the Kings ear, who immediately going to her, upbraids her with Perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; who having nothing elſe to ſay in her own vindication,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170822:55"/> tells him that the Prince intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to marry her. The King with this returns with all the ſpeed that a Jealous Fury could ſupply, and cauſes the Mother of this Prince to come before him, to whom he Complains, and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens that the Prince, (who he ſaid was too often guilty of ſuch faults to be pardon'd) ſhould be rigorouſly puniſh'd; Telling her,
<q>that he expected on the pain of his ſevereſt diſpleaſure, that he ſhould perform what he had promis'd to the Counteſs, which was to marry her; and that though he could ſuffer that his Miſtreſſes ſhould be eſpouſed, yet not that they ſhould other ways be enjoy'd, and that it was for the alone ſake of the Mother (her ſelf) that he Pardon'd the Son.</q> The Princeſs being in a ſtation,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170822:56"/> ſhe thought, above ſuch Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the King, anſwer'd with ſo much Indignation, and rais'd the King into ſo high a Paroxiſme, that he ſent his Guards immediately to ſeize him, and all the favour that could be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd for him by his Friends was that he ſhould relinquiſh the Realm never to return to it again, and he was not recall'd again till the death of the King.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Montpenſier</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before theſe things was dead, and the King, whoſe unfix'd and wandering Apetite induc'd him ſtill to the perſuit of new Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, and to gratifie himſelf in all Varieties of his Inclination, reſolv'd to make Love to his Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, wiſely penſitating, that it would more become his Quality
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170822:56"/> to Love, and be beloved of a Princeſs, than ſuch that was of a meaner Extraction, and indeed no better than fair Impoſters that did only banter and deceive him.</p>
            <p>And reſolv'd to ſerve himſelf upon this occaſion, of a Lord of his Court, equip'd with all the poſſible Accompliſhments of his Quality, (his Name was Count <hi>de Craimail,</hi> making known this deſign to him. He judg'd it a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult thing to bring to effect, but however promiſeth the King to tell her the news.</p>
            <p>The Neighbourhood of his Houſe to that of the Dutcheſſes, and the excellency of his Addreſs was the reaſon of the King's employing of him in this affair, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170822:57"/> to undertake, if the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs would hearken, which yet he could not believe. He acted ſo well in the buſineſs that he prevail'd with the Dutcheſs to come to the Court, where the King ſoon diſcover'd the impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of her Vertue, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd no more to attempt it.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> was now ſo much in Love with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of <hi>Vernueil,</hi> that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to Marry her; and the Marchioneſs willing to make uſe of his Paſſion, either to inflame the King that began to neglect her, to a greater obſervance, or to oblige the Duke irrevertibly to his Promiſe, cauſes in the name of ſome other Perſons (reſerving that due reſpect to their Quality, not to do it in their own) the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170822:57"/> Bains to be publiſhed betwixt them. Which the King hearing of, was greatly enrag'd with them both, and eſpecially with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> But his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions knowing him to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, grew ſo clamorous upon the Marchioneſs, as the only Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this action, on purpoſe to render him odious to the King, that it went no farther, the Duke only retiring to his Government till the rumour was a little ceas'd.</p>
            <p>The Queen having again taken up her deſign of making the Ball before hinted; amongſt the Ladies that was engag'd in it, the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Madam of <hi>Montmorency,</hi> was one; a Lady ſo young, that ſhe had but juſt as it were left to be Child, and ſo Beautiful, that ſhe was miraculous, and in her actions ſo agreeable, that ſhe was a Marvail throughout, inſomuch
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170822:58"/> that the King ſeeing her dance with a Dart in her Hand, repreſenting one of the Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> found his Heart ſo throughly pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with it, that the wound ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd him to his Grave.</p>
            <p>It would fill a Volume ſhould I recount all the Accidents of this Amour, from which at laſt the Royal Lover raviſh'd by Death, left ſuch Subjects behind him, as could not ſo properly be ſaid to Love, as Adore him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170822:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
